hey everyone welcome back to this task
automation playlist and we are
continuing to talk about Tosca best
practices
now this is the second video in this
series
now if you've not watched the first
video go ahead and watch the first video
on Tosca best practices
and then I would also recommend you to
subscribe to our channel so that you
don't miss out on the remaining videos
on this very topic
now coming to Tosca best practice number
two
so we are going to talk about
verification points in test cases
now verification points are absolute
necessary in any test case which you
develop or design with any particular
automation Tool uh for automating any
particular test cases okay so without
verification points your test case will
be considered as incomplete
and the reason is very simple if you
don't have a verification point then you
don't know whether the expected result
is matching the actual result
so the overall purpose of the test case
is not met if you don't have anything to
verify
so it will always be a false positive
right so no matter if your verification
is passing or feeling the test case will
pass if you don't have a verification
point
so every test case should have at least
one or even more verification points
and these verifications will actually
make your test case link to your
requirements right so whatever uh
validations are being done on the test
case will be done as verification points
in your automated test case
okay
so it's very important and let's see
what will happen in Tosca if you don't
have a verification point and what will
happen if you have a verification point
now let's consider a very simple example
for this particular best practice so you
have got a login screen where you enter
an email and a password and then click
on login and then it will login into
your application right
and you're trying to automate this
particular scenario now you will write
the test case or you will Design the
test case so that it can identify those
fields and it can enter the values there
it can click on login
and then maybe you will log out of the
application
so in this whole scenario you must have
one verification point right so for
example once you login into application
you want to make sure that login was
successful right
so maybe you will come here and on the
home page you will check whether the
logout link is appearing right so that
could be your verification similarly for
any particular test case any scenario
you should find out the verification
points right
now coming back to Tosca okay so here is
my login user test case and you can see
here I'm clicking on the login I am
entering the login credentials and then
I'm clicking on the login button
and then here I am also verifying
um the login right where I'm verifying
whether this logout link is visible
equals to true and then the action mode
is verify that but let's first disable
this and let's see what will be the
result of this test case okay
so if I go here
and let me log out from this application
so that it is in that particular State
and let me run this now
and you will see that this test case
will obviously pass okay because a Tosca
will only verify till it is able to
click on that login link after that it
doesn't matter what uh is your output
okay from the application
even if the application doesn't log in
and you get a separate page or a login
failure Tosca is not going to uh
give you a failure because you haven't
written or you haven't designed your
test case according to that right so
this test case is always going to pass
and also in the login info you will not
have any kind of verification right so
any expected or actual result won't be
shown it will be only the steps uh so if
it is able to find this controls it will
always pass okay and that's the
disadvantage of having a test case like
this without any verification point
because there is no purpose of this it
can obviously run but it is not actually
solving your purpose of verifying this
particular test case Okay so whether it
is actually doing what is what it is
supposed to do right
so now if I enable this verification
step and if I go ahead and
let me log out again
and let me go ahead and run this again
okay
and this time around you will see that
there would be an additional
verification step
and if it is not able to find the logout
link so if the logout link is not
present in the application it will fail
this test case obviously it is present
now so it will pass it but in scenarios
where this particular link is missing
then your test case will field right and
that's the expected result which you
want you want to verify something so
that when the application is not
responding as per the expectations then
that should be a failure okay
so here you can see verification was
successful expected value was this
actual value was this right so you need
this for every test case and it should
also be part of your report right
otherwise you will never get any defects
and you should always log a defect
whenever you find a failure a bug or
when the actual result is not matching
the expected result right
so this is why verification points are
important in any automation uh no matter
if you use Tosca or any other automation
tool but especially uh coming to Tosca
when you execute a particular test case
so in the results if you want
um some verification results in your
test steps then you need to have a
verification point okay
so that's all for this video I hope you
enjoyed it and you learned something new
today so keep watching this series of
videos on best practices and keep on
improving your automated test cases if
you are developing them for your project
or for your own purpose in Tosca
so until the next video keep watching
and keep learning